Guide to the Max A. Lauffer Papers, 1915-2013 UA.90.F99
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Extracurricular Involvments, 1952-2011; V.
  - Pitt Activities, 1956-1987; 1.
    - Task Force- Preliminary and Minority Reports, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Provost's Office- Department of Biological Sciences Comprehensive Self-Study, September 1984 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Provost's Office- University Plan 1985-1990, Preliminary Recommendations, November 29, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Provost's Office- University Plan 1985-1990, Final Recommendations, March 1, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Provost's Office- University Plan, A Report to Trustees, June 1985 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Provost's Office- Evaluations, Basic Biological Sciences Departments, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Provost's Office- Faculty of Arts and Sciences/FAS, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Provost's Office- Department Visits, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Provost's Office- Department Visits, FAS, 1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Provost's Office- Department Visits, Engineering, 1985-1987 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Provost's Office- Department Visits, Medicine, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Provost's Office- Department Visits, Medicine, Research and Training Programs Book, 1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Provost's Office- Department Visits, Public Health, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Provost's Office- Biological Sciences Evaluation, 1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Provost's Office- Engineering Review, 1984-1986 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Provost's Office- Pymatuning Laboratory of Ecology Review, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Provost's Office- Technology Transfer, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Provost's Office- Brainstorming Session on Technology Transfer, Cassette, April 24, 1986 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Provost's Office- Brainstorming Session on Technology Transfer, Poster, April 24, 1986 (Map-case 5-6, Oversize 1)
    - Provost's Office- Faculty Unionization, 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Provost's Office- Visit, Duke University, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Provost's Office- Visit, Stanford University, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - Provost's Office- Visit, University of California Berkeley, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Provost's Office- Visit, University of Iowa, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Provost's Office- Visit, University of Michigan, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Provost's Office- Visit, University of Virginia, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - Provost's Office- Visit, Yale University, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Annual Report, Division of the Natural Sciences, 1956-1962 (Box 16, Folder 32)
    - Closing Speaker, Andrew Lowy Memorial Seminar Room Dedication Ceremonies, May 25, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Chair, University of Pittsburgh Tenure Commission- Report, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Science Activities, 1966-2011; 2.
    This subseries consists of material related to Lauffer's involvement in various scientific organizations, such as the Biophysical Society, of which he was a founder and lifelong member.
    - Member, National Advisory General Medical Sciences Council- Photograph, June 1966 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors, Health Research and Services Foundation, 1955-1980 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Founding Member, Biophysical Society, 1968-2011 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Biophysical Society Membership Directory, 2011 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Religious Activities, 1952-2011; 3.
    This subseries contains material regarding Lauffer's involvement with the Presbyterian Church. He was a member of various organizations within the United Presbyterian Church and participated in many committees and conferences, as well as editing the Social Progress journal.
    - Board of Trustees, Pittsburgh Theological Seminary, 1965-1990 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Member, Board of Christian Education, United Presbyterian Church, 1963-1979 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Member and Chair, UPC Council on Church and Society, 1964-1973 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Member, UPC Counseling Committee on Church and Society, 1966-1967 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Member, UPC Advisory Committee on International Affairs, 1964-1968 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - "Social Progress: A Journal of Church and Society," Board of Christian Education, United Presbyterian Church, 1963-1964 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - "Social Progress: A Journal of Church and Society," Board of Christian Education, United Presbyterian Church, 1965, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - "Social Progress: A Journal of Church and Society," Board of Christian Education, United Presbyterian Church, 1968-1969 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Delegate, World Council of Churches, Conference on Church and Society, Task for Member for UPC, July 12-26, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Session Member and Chair of Church and Community Commission, Southminster Presbyterian Church, 1952-1984 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Chair, Advisory Committee on Conscience and Conscription, Southminster Presbyterian Church, 1969-1972 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Advisory Council on Conscience and Conscription- Conscience, Conscription, and the Church, 1967-1969 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Advisory Council on Conscience and Conscription- Alternative Service for Conscientious Objectors, 1969-1970 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Advisory Council on Conscience and Conscription- Selective Service and the Draft, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Board Member, Presbyterian Association on Science, Technology, and the Christian Faith, 1995-2011 (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Other Activities, 1960-2003; 4.
    This subseries consists of material related to Lauffer's involvement in organizations that are not specifically scientific, religious, or related to Pitt. This includes serving as a professor at the University of the Philippines and as a Citizen Ambassador to China.
    - Board Member, Pittsburgh Chapter of World Federalist Association, 1960-1967 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Board Member, College of Wooster, 1969-2002 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Consultant of the Rockefeller Foundation in the Natural Sciences Program, University of the Philippines, October 2-November 15, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Visiting Professor of Physics in the College of Arts and Sciences, University of the Philippines, October 2-November 15, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Member and Officer, Rotary International, Middletown, PA, 1989-2003 (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - Member of Biophysics Delegation, Citizen Ambassador Program, People to People International, China, November 9-30, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - Journal, People to People Biophysics Delegation, China, November 9-30, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Citizen Ambassador Program- Brochures and Booklets, November 9-30, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Member, Penn State Alumni Association (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Assorted Membership Cards (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Course Outlines and Lecture Notes, 1931-1984; VI.
  This series consists of material that Lauffer used for the various courses that he taught at the University of Pittsburgh. It contains course outlines, lecture notes and slides, and other material that he used to instruct his classes. It is arranged chronologically by the year in which the course was taught, though there is also general material for classes that were not specified.
  - "Theoretical Chemistry," ABCh 425, 1931 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - "Food Analysis," ABCh 404, 1932 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - "Soils," 1048, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - General Biophysics, 1945-1946 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Biophysics 278, 1946-1964 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Biometry 174, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - An Outline of Biometric Analysis by Alan E. Treloar (1935), for Biometry 174 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - An Outline of Biometric Analysis Part II: Further Studies in Correlational Analysis by Alan E. Treloar (1935), for Biometry 174 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - "Biometry," Physics E174/Biology E172, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Biophysics Curriculum, 1950 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - "Biometry," Biophysics 173, 1950 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - "Theory of Biophysical Methods," Biophysics 277, 1951, 1953-1955, 1957, 1959, 1961, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Physiology Course- Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole, MA, 1953-1955 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Biophysics E174, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Random Sampling Distributions by Alan E. Treloar (1952), for Biophysics 174 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Biometry 264, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Life Sciences 80, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - "Theology and Science," Pittsburgh Theological Seminary, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - "Thermodynamics and Biology," B&M 377, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - Biophysics and Microbiology 378, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Life Sciences 80, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Biophysics 377, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Biophysics and Microbiology 129, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Biophysics and Microbiology 378, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Biophysics and Microbiology 377, 1973 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - "Entropy-Driven Processes in Biology," B&M 152/BS 124, 1974-1979 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - "Molecular Biology," Life Sciences 21, 1975-1976 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - "Entropy-Driven Processes in Biology," Life Sciences 124, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - "Molecular Biology," Life Sciences 21, 1977 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Life Sciences 377, 1977 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Biological Sciences 21- Transparencies, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Life Sciences 21, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Life Sciences 378, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Material for unidentified course, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Biological Sciences 124, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - "Section on Biophysical Methods," Biological Sciences 212, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Life Sciences 377, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Biological Sciences 124, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Biological Sciences 377, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Biological Sciences 378, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Biological Sciences 337, 1981 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - "Theory of Biophysical Methods," Biological Sciences 378, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - "Theory of Biophysical Methods," Biological Sciences 378- Transparencies, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Biological Sciences 147, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Biological Sciences 377, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Biological Sciences 217, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Biological Sciences 378, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Biostatistics 111 (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - Transparencies for various courses (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - Film Negatives- BS 212 (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Notes and Calculations, 1965-1986; VII.
  This series consists of various notes, calculations, and figures used by Lauffer when writing books and articles or preparing for research. The purpose of many of these notes are unspecified and, therefore, are organized as best as possible to reflect whether they were labelled as "notes," "calculations," or some other specified research material.
  - Calculations, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 29)
  - Calculations and Deductions, 1974-1983 (Box 19, Folder 30-31)
  - Calculations, 1980, 1981, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 32)
  - Calculations, 1981 (Box 19, Folder 33)
  - Notes and Calculations, 1965-1975 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Notes and Calculations from Reprints, 1965-1978 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Laboratory Notes- Stokes' Law, 1965-1970 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Notecards, 1974, 1978 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Notes, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Notes, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Notes on Radiation, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Notes on Properties of Alcohol (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Notes on Assorted Science Topics (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Notes- Biometry (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Notes- Technical (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Notes- Journal (Box 20, Folder 12-14)
  - Notes from courses and book chapters (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Notes for slides- CMU/Shalaby (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Slides- Assorted Notes and Lectures (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Assorted Notes (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Figures and Tables- Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Figures- "Motion in Biological Systems" (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Figures for plates- Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Reprints- Subject Classification, Department of Biophysics (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Slides- Assorted Figures and Graphs (Box 24, Folder 6-8)
  - Film Negatives- Assorted Figures and Graphs (Box 24, Folder 9)
- Honors and Awards, 1944-2003; VIII.
  This series contains documentation of various honors and awards given to Lauffer, including grants that he received over the course of his career. It also contains the physical awards themselves, such as medals and plaques.
  - Summary of Grants Received, 1944-1984 (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - The Eli Lilly and Company Research Award for Fundamental Research in Biological Chemistry, Administered by the American Chemical Society, 1945 (Box 23, Item 1)
  - One of Pittsburgh's Leaders of Tomorrow Award Medal, Presented by The Chamber of Commerce of Pittsburgh and TIME, June 18, 1953 (Box 23, Item 2)
  - The Scaife-Buhl Grants, 1955-1956 (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - American Chemical Society Pittsburgh Award, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - American Chemical Society Pittsburgh Award Plaque, 1958 (Box 23, Item 3)
  - University of Pittsburgh Andrew Mellon Professor Medal, 1963-1984 (Box 23, Item 4)
  - Outstanding Achievement Award of the University of Minnesota, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - Outstanding Achievement Award of the University of Minnesota Medal, 1964 (Box 23, Item 5)
  - The Marquis Who's Who Publications Board Certificates, 1976-1977, 1980-1983 (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - The Commission on Higher Education of the Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools Certificate of Outstanding and Dedicated Service, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 27)
  - Samuel and Carolyn Williams Mission and Peacemaking Award, July 2003 (Box 20, Folder 28)
  - Rotary International Paul Harris Fellow Award (Box 20, Folder 29)
  - Rotary International Paul Harris Fellow Award Medal (Box 23, Item 6)
  - College of Wooster Appreciation Paperweight (Box 23, Item 7)
- Personal Material, 1915-2012; IX.
  This series consists of personal material that is largely unrelated to Lauffer's career or involvement in professional organizations. Included are his personal date books that span almost fifty years. There is also an assortment of personal material that did not fit anywhere else in the collection, such as coursework from his college years and photographs of his high school and college friends. There is also material that was used at his memorial service, including several photographs and articles that span his lifetime.
  - Biographical Information, 1963-1970; 1.
    This subseries contains biographical information and data books that detail Lauffer's work history, publications, and other information at various points in his life.
    - Biographical Information (Box 23, Folder 30)
    - Biographical Data Book, 1963-1964 (Box 23, Folder 31)
    - Biographical Data Book, 1965-1966 (Box 23, Folder 32)
    - Biographical Data Book, 1967-1968 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Biographical Data Book, 1969-1970 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Date Books, 1958-2004; 2.
    This subseries contains Lauffer's date books from approximately fifty years of his life. These outline his daily schedules, appointments, contact information, and other personal data.
    - Date Books, 1958, 1961-1963 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Date Books, 1964-1967 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Date Books, 1968-1971 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Date Books, 1972-1975 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Date Books, 1976-1979 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Date Books, 1980-1983 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Date Books, 1984-1987 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Date Books, 1988-1991 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Date Books, 1992-1995 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Date Books, 1996-1999 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Date Books, 2000-2004 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Assorted Personal Material, 1929-1987; 3.
    This subseries consists of material from Lauffer's personal life that is not directly related to his career. This includes some examples of college coursework, diplomas, programs from ceremonies, and index cards taken from his personal address book.
    - Middletown High School Diploma, June 13, 1929 (Map-case 5-6, Oversize 1)
    - Penn State Grade Books, 1933 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 14)
    - Coursework at the University of Minnesota, 1933-1937 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 15-16)
    - University of Minnesota Grade Books, 1934-1935 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 17)
    - "Peaks of Progress" Award Selection Form, 1946-1947 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 18)
    - Ocean Times, January 16, 1953 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 19)
    - Langley and Crawford Hall Dedications, 1961, 1969 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 20)
    - Self-Evaluation Reports, 1980, 1982 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 21)
    - Franklin & Marshall Application Letter and Curriculum Vitae, 1987 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 22)
    - Personal Address Book: A-E (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Personal Address Book: F-L (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Personal Address Book: M-R (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Personal Address Book: S-Z (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Slides- Unknown Event (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Memorial Service Material, 1915-2012; 4.
    This subseries contains the material used for Lauffer's memorial service, including photographs of friends and family and articles that were used for display. This subseries also includes a DVD of the memorial service.
    - Memorial Service Material, October 7, 2012 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Photographs of High School and College Friends (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Retirement Photograph- with Jonas Salk, May 17, 1984 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Assorted Photographs from Memorial Service, 1915-2012 (Box 22, Folder 8)
- 2017 Addition, 1929-1984; X.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material donated to the collection in 2017. It includes awards given to Lauffer as well as some publications and talks. Also documented here is Lauffer's early academic and professional career at the University of Minnesota and Pennsylvania State University.
  - American Chemical Society Pittsburgh Section Award Photos and Program, December 11, 1958 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Alpha Chi Sigma Fraternity Membership Certificate, May 16, 1936 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Alpha Zeta Fraternity House at Penn State, 1931-1934 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Photos from Minnesota, July 7, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Edward H. Litchfield about Jonas Salk, Photocopy, March 14-16, 1960 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - "Electric Forces At Organic Liquid-Solid Interfaces," University of Minnesota Graduate School Thesis and Calculations, May 1937 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Eli Lily Award Article, 1945 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Gamma Alpha Graduate Scientific Fraternity Certificate, February 7, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Journal Entries, September 2-3, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Letters about Research, September 7-10, 1943 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Molecular Biology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Entropy-Driven Processes in Biology, Polymerization of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein and Similar Reactions by Max A. Lauffer, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - Peaks of Progress Breakfast Program, June 2, 1947 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Pennsylvania State College High School Transcript, August 19, 1929 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Pittsburgh Theological Seminary Executive Board Member Plaque, May 12, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - "Planetarium Parade" Script, October 17, 1946 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Retirement Symposium Poster, April 27, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Sanitary Engineering Center Dedication Program, April 8-9, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Society of Sigma Xi Event Programs, 1937-1951 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - The Society of The Sigma Xi Certificate, May 24, 1937 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - University of Minnesota Commencement Booklet, June 14, 1937 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - University of Pittsburgh Events Pamphlets, 1952-1957 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Viral and Rickettsial Infections of Man 1st Edition Edited by Thomas M. Rivers, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Viral and Rickettsial Infections of Man 2nd Edition Edited by Thomas M. Rivers, 1952 (Box 26, Folder 9)